DAN KLEIN: From this example, we can
see that for A star graph search,
we're going to need a stronger
condition than admissibility.
The basic idea of this new condition
is going to be the same as for
admissibility, and that is that
estimated heuristic costs will have to
be less than or equal to actual costs.
What did admissibility do?
It said that the heuristic cost, which
was an estimate of a cost to the goal,
had to be less than or equal to
the actual cost to the goal.
So for example, if you have a node A,
then admissibility says that heuristic
value A must be less than or equal to
the actual cost from A to the goal in
the optimal way.
For example, if h is four at A, and
here's the goal of G, then h equals
four is describing the length from A
to G according to the heuristic.
According to the actual cost, there is
some shortest path from A to G. And in
this case, that shortest path
also has cost four.
So here, h equals four is
admissible in this case.
What we need for A star graph search to
be correct is the stronger notion
of consistency.
Consistency says that the heuristic cost
must be less than or equal to the
actual cost for each arc, not just
the path towards the goal.
So what does that look like?
It looks at a single arc, and it says,
OK here's a real arc, which has cost
one in this case.
If the real cost is one, what
is the cost of this arc
according to the heuristic?
Well, heuristics don't
actually score arcs.
But if you think about it, if the
heuristic is four at A, and it's one
at C, like in our example, then really
if you look at the heuristic, it looks
like this arc cost three.
In particular, you can look at the
difference in heuristic value from A
to C and say that that difference must
be less than or equal to the actual
cost from A to C. That is consistency.
Now, in this case, where A star went
wrong, we can see that this arc is not
consistent.
h equals four is admissible, and so
is h equals one, but because the
heuristic implies a cost of three, where
the real arc only costs one,
this is not a consistent heuristic.
To make it consistent,
we could lower h.
For example, we could make h equal
two at A. And now we have
a consistent heuristic.
If you went back and ran the same
example with this change to the
heuristic, you would get the correct
optimal result from A star.
What are the consequences
of consistency?
Well, one consequence is that
the f value along the
path will never decrease.
Why is that?
If you go from a parent A to a child C,
then at A you added in h of A, the
heuristic A. And at C, you add in the
cost from A to C and then the
heuristic value at C.
Consistency, by simple rewriting,
guarantees that that is an increase.
The result of this is that A star
graph search is optimal.
Why is A star graph search going to be
optimal with a consistent heuristic?
We'll sketch the proof.
First, let's consider what A star does
when it has a consistent heuristic.
The first fact is that because of
consistency, A star will expand nodes
in increasing total f value.
The second fact is that for every state
S, nodes that reach S optimally
are expanded before nodes that
reach S suboptimally.
Once we have these two facts proven,
we'll have the result that A star
graph search is optimal because
in particular, fact two will
hold at goal states.